Norma Kidd Green Papers
Norma Kidd Green Papers
1844-2016
1950-1980
Green, Norma Kidd.
4 linear ft.
Collection includes correspondence and writings of the American author, including Iron Eye's Family and A Forgotten Chapter in American Education, as well as her childhood books and books by early American educator Jane Andrews.
2728917
Biographical History
Norma Kidd Green (1893-1975) was an American author.
A graduate of Beatrice High School in 1911 and the University of Nebraska in 1915, Green was an accomplished writer. Among her publications are a biography of early American educator Jane Andrews and Iron Eye's Family, about the children of Omaha chief Iron Eye (Joseph LaFlesche). Kidd married Roy Melvin Green in 1919 and had four children: Mary Elizabeth (Betty), Nancy Josephine (Nan), William Earl (Bill) and Thomas Franklin (Tom).
Green was deeply interested in the education of women, the lives of Native Americans, and in promoting the habits of life-long learning. She is well known for her Biography by Books in which she set out to portray her own life as a narrative informed by books, particularly those works that were important in her childhood; many of these books are included in the collection. In 1952, Green gave a copy of her story to each of her three living children, and it has since been revised and passed down along the "Green-Genes." This book provides a narrative of Norma Green's life, including the death of her son Bill in World War II and her focus on foreign affairs, activism, and her renewed efforts on becoming a teacher.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Norma Kidd Green Papers consist of correspondence, memorabilia, printed materials, and writings.
Correspondence contains incoming and outgoing correspondence with the American Foundation for the Blind, Nebraska City School for the Blind, and the Nebraska State Historical Society.
Memorabilia includes diaries, journals, photographs, scrapbooks and other items. Of interest is Green's commencement program from Beatrice High School.
Printed materials is subdivided into writings by Green, by others, and by unknown authors. The majority of these are books that were important in Green's childhood, which she describes in her Biography by Books. While some of the books predate Green's lifetime, these are books that have been passed down through her family and are relevant to her work and character.
Writings comprises typed and handwritten manuscripts of various articles, essays, etc written by Green. Of special interest are three editions of her Biography by Books, research for her book Iron Eye's Family, and manuscripts for a history of the Young Women's Christian Association of the University of Nebraska, Green's alma mater.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Memorabilia is sorted first alphabetically by type or topic. then chronologically. Printed materials are subdivided into writings by Green, by others, and by unknown authors. Within these sections, items are sorted alphabetically by author and title. Writings are sorted alphabetically by title.
Related Material
Additional Norma Kidd Green material is available at the Nebraska State Historical Society, including the LaFlesche Family Papers collected by Green. See also the Norma Kidd Green Papers at the Smith College Special Collections.
Subject and Genre Headings
Biography; Women Authors; Alcott, Louisa May, 1832-1888.; Andrews, Jane, 1833-1887.; Arnold, Sarah Louise, 1859-1943.; Gilbert, Charles B. (Charles Benajah), 1855-1913.; Green, Norma Kidd.; LaFlesche, Joseph, 1822-1889.; American Foundation for the Blind.; Nebraska State Historical Society.; Children's literature -- 19th century.; Children's literature, American -- Bio-bibliography.; Women authors, American.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Manuscripts for publication.; Memorabilia.; Research notes.; Biographers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Thomas F. Green, 2000.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - American Foundation for the Blind, undated (Box 1)
  - Nebraska City School for the Blind, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Nebraska State Historical Society, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Opocensky, Virginia, 2016 (Box 1)
  - Town Journal, 1956; includes typescript of article submitted by Green (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Beatrice High School Commencement Program, 1911 (Box 1)
  - BIOG.NKG.WPD, green_nk_001; most likely Green's biography; WordPerfect format (files not viewed); Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1941; 1958 (Box 1)
  - "Cuttings from Diaries of Norma Kidd (Green)", handwritten excerpts from from 1911-1971 (Box 1)
  - Funeral guest book, Norma Kidd Green, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Funeral guest book, Roy M. Green, 1976; includes program from memorial service (Box 1)
  - Guest book, 1927-1952 (Box 1)
  - Journals, 1957-1959; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Journal, undated; scattered notes, many blank pages (Box 2)
  - Photograph album, undated; candid shots of cabin in woods, people (Oversize 1)
  - Photographs, 1942; 1961,; undated; includes clipping of article by Green, which uses one of the photos (Box 2)
  - "Reading Record", 1957-1968 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbooks, undated; clippings, notes, copies of quotes and poems, etc.; 2 volumes (Box 2)
- Printed materials
  - By Green
    - Articles, miscellaneous, 1930-1931; 1942,; 1955,; 1957 (Box 2)
      See also Writings: Articles, miscellaneous below.
    - A Forgotten Chapter in American Education: Jane Andrews of Newburyport, 1961; signed and inscribed to Rose Riddell (Box 2)
    - Books And You, 1956 (Box 2)
  - By others
    - Alcott, Louisa M. Eight Cousins or, the Aunt Hill, 1895 (Box 4)
    - Alcott, Louisa M. Rose in Bloom, 1886 (Box 4)
    - Andrews, Jane Each and All :The Seven Little Sisters Prove their Sisterhood, 1905 (Box 4)
    - Andrews, Jane Geographical Plays, 1880 (Box 4)
    - Andrews, Jane The Rational Spelling Book, undated (Box 4)
    - Andrews, Jane Seven Little Sisters, 1895 (Box 4)
    - Andrews, Jane The Stories of My Four Friends, 1900 (Box 4)
    - Andrews, Jane The Stories Mother Nature Told Her Children, 1895 (Box 4)
    - Andrews, Jane Ten Boys Who Lived on the Road from long ago to now, 1885 (Box 4)
    - Arnold, Sarah Louise and Gilbert, Charles B. Stepping Stones to Literature: A First Reader, 1902 (Box 4)
    - Arnold, Sarah Louise and Gilbert, Charles B. Stepping Stones to Literature: A Second Reader, 1902 (Box 4)
    - Arnold, Sarah Louise and Gilbert, Charles B. Stepping Stones to Literature: A Third Reader, 1897 (Box 4)
    - Arnold, Sarah Louise and Gilbert, Charles B. Stepping Stones to Literature: A Reader for Sixth Grades, 1897 (Box 4)
    - Arnold, Sarah Louise and Gilbert, Charles B. Stepping Stones to Literature: A Reader for Seventh Grades, 1898 (Box 5)
    - Arnold, Sarah Louise and Gilbert, Charles B. Stepping Stones to Literature: A Reader for Higher Grades, 1898 (Box 5)
    - Crabtree, J. W. The Roll of Honor Word Book, undated (Box 5)
    - Goddard, Julia Fairy Tales in Other Lands, 1892 (Box 5)
  - No author or unknown
    - Jingles and Chimes, undated (Box 4)
    - Picture Lessons in English Part 1, undated (Box 4)
    - Tip Toe Days, 1893 (Box 4)
    - The Twentieth Century New Testament, undated (Box 4)
    - The Youth's Keepsake, 1844 (Box 4)
- Writings
  - Articles, miscellaneous, typescript, some with corrections, some annotated with publication date and venue (Box 2)
  - Biography By Books
    - First edition, 1952; typescript (Box 2)
    - Second edition, 1977; typescript (Box 2)
    - Third edition, 2000; typescript, multiple copies; a few pages of handwritten notes (Box 2)
    - Typescript, third edition, 2000; typescript, multiple copies, one in red cover (Box 3)
    - Typescript of addendum, "Tuesday Morning Study Club", 2000 (Box 3)
  - The First Seventy-Five Years of the Young Women's Christian Association of the University of Nebraska
    - "Good Copy", 1915; typescript (Box 3)
    - "Irregular Copy", 1915; typescript with handwritten notes (Box 3)
  - Iron Eye's Family: the Children of Joseph LaFlesche
    - Clippings, 1961; 1981 (Box 3)
    - Research notes, undated (Box 3)
    - Writings, 1961-1975 (Box 3)
  - Notes, miscellaneous, undated (Box 3)
  - Poetry, undated; handwritten scraps (Box 3)
  - Toast. Mother-Daughter Banquet, undated; includes handwritten notes (Box 3)
  - Unknown, undated; copies of poems; typescript fragment (Box 3)